Have you ever watched one of the many TV shows set during the apocalypse - a dystopian future where life as we know it is over and people are only focussed on survival?
你是否看过那些以末日为背景的电视剧——在反乌托邦的未来，我们熟知的生活已然终结，人们一心只想着活下去？
If it’s not zombies, it’s viruses or natural disasters.
故事的导火索不是僵尸来袭，就是病毒肆虐或自然灾害爆发。
One thing that seems to be a quintessential part of these series is survivors searching for food and resources.
这类剧集的一个典型特征，就是幸存者四处搜寻食物和资源。
Is that why people stockpile food when things go bad?
难道这就是世道艰难时人们会囤积食物的原因吗？
What is stockpiling?
什么是囤积？
Quite simply it’s when people accumulate a substantial number of goods, for example food or water.
很简单，就是人们大量囤积物资，比如食物或水。
According to psychologist Judy Rosenberg, stockpiling perishable goods like eggs and milk is a positive sign that people believe a crisis will be over soon.
心理学家朱迪·罗森伯格表示，囤积鸡蛋、牛奶这类易腐物资，是人们相信危机很快就会过去的积极信号。
When people stockpile tinned goods, it can be a sign that people fear that the crisis will endure.
而如果囤积的是罐装食品，则可能意味着人们担心危机将会持续很长时间。
But why do we do it?
但我们为什么会这么做呢？
Consumer psychologist Paul Marsden puts it down to three factors that relate to retail therapy.
消费心理学家保罗·马斯登将其归结为与购物疗法相关的三个因素。
Firstly, ‘autonomy’ – the idea the people feel the need to be in control.
第一是“自主掌控感”——人们会觉得自己需要掌控局面。
Secondly, ‘relatedness’ – panic shopping helps people to feel connected to the community or other shoppers who are doing the same.
第二是“归属感”——恐慌性购物会让人们觉得自己和社区里的人，或是和其他同样在抢购的人产生了联结。
Lastly, ‘competence’ - people want to feel like they are ‘smart shoppers’ and doing the right thing.
第三是“价值感”——人们希望自己能成为“精明的购物者”，做的事情是正确的。
Sander Van der Lindon, an assistant professor of social psychology at Cambridge University, said that a phenomenon known as ‘fear contagion’ can take hold.
剑桥大学社会心理学助理教授桑德·范德林登表示，一种名为“恐惧传染”的现象可能会随之蔓延。
People’s decision making is hampered when stressed, so they follow the actions of other people.
人在压力之下，决策能力会受到影响，因此会下意识模仿他人的行为。
If they are panic buying, you will too.
如果别人都在恐慌性抢购，你也会跟着这么做。
So, can you stop people from stockpiling?
那么，有办法阻止人们囤积物资吗？
Well, supermarkets can ration the amount of products consumers purchase, and governments can try to reassure people that there is no need to panic.
超市可以对消费者的购买量进行定量供应，政府也可以努力安抚民众，让大家不必恐慌。
However, it seems that it goes against our basic psychology to try and stop people from panic buying.
但事实似乎是，阻止人们进行恐慌性购物，是违背人类基本心理的。
So, the next time a virus, natural disaster or zombie apocalypse starts, remember that panic buying is probably a given, thanks to our need for retail therapy to manage our emotional state.
所以下次再遇到病毒蔓延、自然灾害或是僵尸末日这样的情况时，要记住恐慌性购物或许是必然会发生的——毕竟我们需要靠购物疗愈来调节自己的情绪状态。